Guide to the Asian Women's Institute - North American Office Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Asian Women's Institute - North American Office Records
1960-1993
RG 106
Yale University Divinity School Library
24
(51 boxes)
Minutes, correspondence, printed material, and administrative records document the creation of the AWI and its development into an organization led primarily by Asian women. The archives also contain documentation related to the Asian women's colleges that were members of the AWI. The Asian Women's Institute was created in 1975 as a catalyst organization motivating Christian colleges for women in Asia to focus attention and resources on the major needs of women in their respective countries and to build a cooperative network among the thirteen member institutions. For many years the AWI had a New York office as well as an international office, but after the early 1990s the majority of its activities were handled through the international office.
Asian Women's Institute
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Asia Women's Institute, New York Office.
Biographical / Historical
1971 Apr Beirut University College, Beirut, Lebanon Kinnaird College for Women, Lahore, Pakistan Ewha Woman's University, Seoul, Korea Seoul Woman's University; Seoul, Korea Madras Women's Christian College, Madras, India Tokyo Woman's Christian University; Tokyo, Japan Isabella Thoburn College, Lucknow, India St. Christopher's College of Education, Madras, India Representatives of the following schools agreed to plan for a joint organzation: Kobe College, Japan Hawabagh Women's College, Jabalpur, India Philippine Women's Institute (Harris Memorial College, Manila, Northern Christian College, Laoag City, and Silliman University, Dumaguete City) Damavand College, Tehran, Iran
1972 May Presidents of the nine original colleges met in Seoul, beginning a pattern of presidential consultations every three years.
1974 Oct Planning Committee for the Asian Women's Institute met prior to Church Women United Assembly in Memphis. Conference of Asian educators in the USA held following Assembly. Support group called the Committee of 75 was formed, with Phebe Gregorian as chairperson.
1975 May Asian Women's Institute was founded during Administrators' Consultation in Beirut. Dr. Eva Shipstone, President of Isabella Thoburn College, was appointed as International Coordinator and Mira Phailbus, Principal of Kinnaird College, was appointed president. A group called the Association of North American Cooperating Agencies of Overseas Women's Christian Colleges was formed as the North American support agency for the AWI. The Program Agency of the Presbyterian Church in the USA contributed office space in New York and the services of Margaret Flory. The work of the Committee of 75 was carried on by Phebe Gregorian in Boston. There were also "clusters" created in various North American cities.
1978 Triennial conference in Tokyo
1979-1981 Career services and continuing education emphasis for the triennium - Commission on Women and Work; activities in conjunction with Wellesley College women's career center.
1981 Jul Triennial conference in Manila
1981-1984 Peacemaking emphasis for the triennium
1981 Association changed its name to Association of Christians for Women's Education in Asia
1982 Santosh Singh was International Coordinator following the retirement of Eva Shipstone
1984-1986 Margaret Flory transferred U. S. leadership to a series of others.
1985 Tenth Anniversary celebration and triennial meeting in Hong Kong (originally scheduled for New Delhi)
1985-1988 Leadership development emphasis for triennium
1986 Association changed its name to Association of Christians for Women's Education and Development in Asia
1988 Triennial conference in Indonesia
1991 Triennial conference at Kobe College, Japan
1991-1994 Leadership of North American association in flux (included Erika Harper, Jean Woo, Beverley Thompson-Travis, Betty Gray); North American contributions becoming sparse. New York office closed and records transferred to YDSL.
Scope and Contents
These records provide fascinating documentation of the creation and development of an organization devoted to the self-realization of women in Asia through education. The AWI and its American support agency emerged at the same time, but now the AWI continues only as an Asian-led organization. The evolving interchange of leadership and power between Asian and American women documented in these records is of interest. The issues addressed by the AWI during the years documented by this collection included career options for Asian women, peacemaking, and leadership development. The AWI published the periodical Asian Woman, sponsored research projects, and in many other ways contributed to mutual exchange and cooperation between the Asian women's colleges it supported. This record group also includes much valuable information about the individual women's colleges in India, Iran, Japan, Korea, Lebanon, and the Philippines that were AWI members.
Series I through V of this record group are parallel streams of documentation, each covering the same years, but from different angles. Series I, History and Overview, traces the events and proposals leading to the establishment of the Asian Women's Institute, gives a succinct view of the evolving policies and activities of the AWI, and documents the relationship of AWI to other organizations. Many of the documents in this series are duplicated in other series, but have been drawn together here to provide an overview of the organization's development.
Series II, Meeting/ Committee Records, includes records of the Asian Women's Institute and its American support agencies. The organizational hierarchy of the archives is a bit confusing because it reflects the interplay between the Asian Women's Institute, its North American support agency called the Association of North American Cooperating Agencies of Overseas Women's Christian Colleges (and later name changes), and the Committee of 75, which had primarily a fundraising function. Subseries headings in Series II indicate which of these groups is being documented.
Series III, Correspondence/ Administrators' Files, contains the administrative files of the Committee of 75 (based in Boston) and the New York office of the AWI/Association. The International Office of the AWI sent carbon copies of correspondence to the New York office, so general AWI records are also included in the Association files.
Series IV, Conferences and Consultations, includes documentation of meetings leading up to the formation of the AWI, meetings of the Asian Women's Institute's constituents such as the Presidents' Consultations and AWI Executive Committee (as opposed to more administrative meetings of the Association support agency, which are documented in Series II), triennial conferences of the AWI, and themed conferences and seminars.
Series V, Programs and Projects, documents specific programs that the AWI sponsored. Of particular interest are the materials related to career development and leadership development among Asian women. These records complement the documentation in Series VI of the women's study centers operating at the Asian women's colleges. The documentation of Series VI by no means gives a complete picture of the work of these Asian women's colleges, but it provides a valuable record of the activities and programs of the colleges' women's study centers.
The Asian Women's Institute, the Association, and the Committee of 75 were all devoted to supporting the colleges' women's study centers and related programs and conferences. Series VII, Publications and Promotional Material, documents the methods used to spread the word about the center and programs. Of particular interest are the files of the periodical Asian Woman, which contained many substantive articles about women's issues in Asia.
Series VIII, Membership Records, and Series IX, Financial Records, contain administrative documentation of the operations of the Association and AWI, as well as documentation of efforts made to solicit grants and funds from other organizations. More material regarding the organizations with which the AWI and Association interacted is contained in Series X, Related Organizations. The material in Series X is less related to financial matters and more related to efforts of the AWI to cooperate with and benefit from other organizations, particularly Church Women United and the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia. Series XI, Collected Material, represents the "subject file" of the organization, materials that they had gathered as resource material.
Series XII, an Addendum added in 2011, includes materials that were received with the Margaret Flory Papers, YDSL RG 86. The materials in this series overlap with those received earlier, as reflected in its subseries.
Arrangement
I. History and Overview
II. Organization / Committee Records
III. Correspondence / Administrators' files
IV. Conferences and Consultations
V. Programs and Projects
VI. Colleges and Centers in Asia
VII. Publications and Promotional Material
VIII.Membership Records
IX. Financial Records
X. Related Organizations
XI. Collected Material
XII. Addendum
Religious education -- Asia; Universities and colleges -- Asia; Educators; Asian Women's Institute
- History and Overview, Series I
  - Documents, proposals leading to establishment of the Asian Women's Institute, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Historical statements re. AWI, 1974-1985, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Statements of objectives and purpose of AWI, 1975, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Project Document for the AWI, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Case Statement of the Asian Women's Institute; incl. diagram of organizational structure (and various drafts), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Constitution of the Asian Women's Institute; Constitution of the Presidents' Consultation, 1978- 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Action plans for AWI, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Documents re. membership policy, 1978, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reports of AWI Coordinator, Eva Shipstone; Report of Communications Secretary, Norah Shipstone, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reports of AWI Coordinator, Santosh Singha, 1982, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reports of Association of the North American Cooperating Agencies of Overseas Women's Christian Colleges, Margaret Flory, Chairperson, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports of Association of Christians for Women's Education in Asia, Margaret Flory, Chairperson, 1983, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reports of Committee of 75; Report of New York office, 1977, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Inquiry re. incorporation of Association of Christians for Women's Education in Asia, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Documents related to relationship of AWI to other organizations, incl. Church Women United, NCCCUSA-DOM, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Organization / Committee Records, Series II
  - Ad Hoc Committee representing U. S. Committees of Women's Christian Colleges Abroad
    - Meeting records - NYC, 1971 Jan (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Association of the North American Cooperating Agencies of Overseas Women's Christian Colleges
    - Annual meetings
      - Organizing meeting; minutes, etc. - NYC, 1971 Oct (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Minutes, etc. - NYC, New Brunswick NJ, 1972 Jan, Jun (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Minutes, etc. - NYC, 1973 Apr (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Minutes, etc. - Fairleigh Dickinson Univ., 1974 Jun (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Minutes, etc. - Stony Point, 1975 Feb-1978 Mar (Box 2, Folder 21-25)
      - Minutes, etc. - Stony Point, 1978 Oct-1979 Nov (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
      - Minutes, etc. - NYC, 1980 Jun (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Minutes, etc. - Stony Point, 1980 Dec- 1981 Nov (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
    - Steering Committee
      - Minutes, etc., 1971 Nov -1975 (Box 3, Folder 33-37)
      - Minutes, correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 38-44)
    - Other Committees
      - Committee to Recommend Guidelines for Association Membership and Responsibility, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Special Committee to Study the Future, 1980 Sep (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Planning Committee for AWI Alumnae Conference, 1980 Jun (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Association of Christians for Women's Education in Asia
    - Annual meetings
      - Minutes, etc., 1982 Jul-1984 (Box 4, Folder 48-50)
      - Agenda, material from Interchurch Center meeting (decision to change name to Assn. of Christians for Women's Education and Development in Asia), 1986 May (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Steering Committee
      - Minutes, etc., 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 52-55)
    - Special Study Committee on USA Base of AWI
      - Corres., memoranda, reports, background material (incl. re. ACWEA relationship with Church Women United), 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 56-58)
    - Support Committee
      - Minutes, corres., 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
  - Association of Christians for Women's Education and Development in Asia
    - Annual meetings
      - Minutes, etc., 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 61-63)
    - Steering Committee
      - Minutes, etc., 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 64-65)
    - Nominating Committee
      - Corres., 1986 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Coordinating Committee
      - Minutes, 1988 Dec (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Committee of Cooperating Colleagues
      - Agenda, memoranda, 1989 Nov (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Committee of 75 (support group)
    - Reports, minutes, memoranda, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 69-71)
  - Asian Women's Institute
    - Executive Committees of AWI and Presidents' Consultation
      - Executive Committee of the Administrators of the Nine Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Tehran, Iran, 1976 Jan (Box 6, Folder 72)
      - Executive Committee of the Administrators of the Nine Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Stony Point, 1977 Jul 11-13 (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
      - Joint meeting of Executive Committees of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Seoul, 1978 May (Box 7, Folder 75)
      - Joint meeting of Executive Committees of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Singapore, 1979 Jul 3-6 (Box 7, Folder 76)
      - Joint meeting of Executive Committees of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Claremont, 1980 Jul 2-4 (Box 7, Folder 77)
      - Executive Committee of AWI - Manila, 1981 Jul 14 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Executive Committee of AWI - Stony Point: Minutes, reports, 1982 Jul 20-26 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - Executive Committee of AWI - Stony Point: Background material, corres., 1982 Jul 20-26 (Box 7, Folder 80)
      - Joint meeting of Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Seoul, 1983 Jul 12-17 (Box 8, Folder 81)
      - Joint meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Stony Point, 1984 Jul 25 (Box 8, Folder 82)
      - Joint meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Hong Kong, 1985 Jan 30-31 (Box 8, Folder 83)
      - Joint meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute; Coordinator's report to the Executive Committee - Stony Point, 1986 May (Box 8, Folder 84)
      - Joint Ad Hoc Meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultations and the Asian Women's Institute - Indonesia, 1988 Jul 4-5 (Box 8, Folder 85)
      - Joint meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents' Consultation and the Asian Women's Institute - Cedar Rapids Iowa, 1990 Aug (Box 8, Folder 86)
      - Joint meeting of the Executive Committee of the Presidents Consultations and the Asian Women's Institute - Japan, 1991 Oct 6-7 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Planning Committee
      - Stony Point meeting, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 88)
- Correspondence/ Administrators' files, Series III
  - Committee of 75 files
    - General corres.; corres. with NY office, 1975-1982, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 89-95)
    - Misc. mailing lists, 1975, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Address lists of alumnae and friends of the colleges (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Invitations to join Committee of 75, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 98-99)
    - Letters of regret from those asked to join Committee, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Corres. with members:; Adair, Adams, Adkins, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Corres. with members: Bacerra, Barbey, Bingham, Bishop, Braunwarth, Briggs, Bunce, Burnham, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Corres. with members: Catchings, Christopher, Clapp, Courtice (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Corres. with members: Dail, Davidson, Dennis, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Corres. with members: Driscoll, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Corres. with members: Dunlap, Elliott, Foster, Gray, Griffin, Hall, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Corres. with members: Flory, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Corres. with members: Hargrove, Hawkins, Hartel, Himaya, Jensen, Jones, Kim, Mathews, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - Corres. with members: Mayer, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - Corres. with members: McCallion, McCort, MItchell, Naylor, Nelson, Pardee, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - Corres. with members: Pratt, Popkin, Riehm, Royer, Rubendall, Ruether, Sattler (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Corres. with members: Sawin, Simpson, Sinclair, Sparrowyk, Stair, Stephenson, Thompson, Tiller, Van Horne, Williams (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Corres. with members: Elizabeth Lam Vieg, 1975-1981 (Box 11, Folder 113-114)
    - Re. Speakers Bureau, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Association files
    - Misc., 1971-1974 (Box 11, Folder 116-119)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Record of mailings from NY Office, 1978-1981 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ notes of Margaret Flory/ outreach, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 132-133)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 135-137)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 138)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 139-141)
    - Corres. with editor of Asian Woman, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 142)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1983 Jan-Jun (Box 14, Folder 144-145)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1983 Jul-Dec (Box 15, Folder 146-147)
    - Corres. with editor of Asian Woman, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 148)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 149-150)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 151-154)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 155-156)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 157-158)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 159-160)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 161-162)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 163)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 164)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 165)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 166)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 167)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 169)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 170)
    - Internal Assn. corres. and with U.S. program agencies/ outreach, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 171)
    - Corres. with AWI International Office and college administrators, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 172)
    - Corres. of AWI International Office and college administrators, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 173)
- Conferences and Consultations, Series IV
  - Consultation on Women's Colleges Overseas -Tuxedo Park, NY, 1971 Apr (Box 18, Folder 174)
  - Administrators Consultation of the Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Seoul: Agenda, report, arrangements, 1972 May (Box 18, Folder 175)
  - Administrators Consultation of the Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Seoul: Papers, speeches, 1972 May (Box 18, Folder 176)
  - Colloquium on Asian Women's Higher Education - Memphis, 1974 Oct 13-14 (Box 18, Folder 177)
  - Administrators Consultation of the Nine Christian Women's Colleges in Asia - Beirut, 1975 May (Box 18, Folder 178)
  - Meeting of Executive Committee of Administrators of the Nine Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Purdue, 1976 Jul 19-21 (Box 18, Folder 179)
  - Workshop on the Asian Women's Institute; Church Women United Assembly - Purdue, 1977 Jul 7-10 (Box 18, Folder 180)
  - Meeting of Executive Committee of the Nine Women's Christian Colleges in Asia - Stony Point, 1977 Jul 10-13 (Box 18, Folder 181)
  - Triennial Presidents' Consultation - Tokyo: transcript of proceedings, May 2, 1978 May 1-5 (Box 19, Folder 182)
  - Triennial Presidents' Consultation - Tokyo: transcript of proceedings, May 3-5, 1978 May 1-5 (Box 19, Folder 183)
  - Triennial Presidents' Consultation - Tokyo: minutes, reports, arrangements, 1978 May 1-5 (Box 19, Folder 184-186)
  - Directors' Workshop - Seoul, 1978 May 8-10 (Box 19, Folder 187)
  - Scholars' Seminar - Seoul, 1978 May 11-13 (Box 20, Folder 188)
  - Career Counselling Conference - Singapore: minutes, arrangements, 1979 Jun 27-Jul 3 (Box 20, Folder 189)
  - Career Counselling Conference - Singapore: report and papers, 1979 Jun 27-Jul 3 (Box 20, Folder 190-191)
  - Consultations on Continuing Education - Korea, Japan, India, Pakistan, Lebanon: arrangements, proposals, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 192)
  - Consultations on Continuing Education - Korea, Japan, India, Pakistan, Lebanon: reports, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 193)
  - Career Counselling Seminar - Manila, 1981 Jun 29- Jul 5 (Box 21, Folder 194-195)
  - Asian Conference on Women's Higher Education - Manila, 1981 Jul 7-10 (Box 21, Folder 196-197)
  - Presidents' Consultation/ Directors' Workparty - Manila, 1981 Jul 11-13 (Box 21, Folder 198-199)